Vaibhav Sabnis

New York | Phone: +1(973) 337 0312 | Email: vaibhav.sabnis@gmail.com | LinkedIn

KEY COMPENTENCIES

Seasoned senior software professional with 20+ years of experience in software development and leadership roles. Technologist with an agile mindset, committed to engineering excellence, simplicity, maintainability, and usability. Highly skilled in setting up and scaling technology organizations, shaping technical vision, mitigating risks, and delivering key business results in Finance and Ads Tech domains. Valued for intellectual curiosity and an empathetic leader, emphasizing the potential of investing in people and teamwork.

Technical Acumen

- Architect, deliver and maintain distributed systems, Infra and APIs that operate for very large scale of users/transactions/machines under high reliability, low latency, and power enveloped constraints.
- Lead technology-driven digital transformation initiatives, including transitions from on-premises to cloud environments and desktop to web technology stack modernization.
- Adapt technical infrastructure and controls for Data Governance, Security and regulatory adherence, primarily for MNPI / PII data categories.
- Proficient across a diverse range of technical tools and stacks within the SDLC process, maintaining a language-agnostic approach.

Organizational Leadership

- Spearhead the setup and expansion of ambitious technical initiatives, leading and optimizing high-performing global software engineering teams, surpassing 100+ engineering org.
- Design and execute organizational and technical vision, strategy, and roadmap, implementing streamlined team structures, organization
 operating rhythm and metrics/OKRs to measure success towards topline goals.
- Adept at establishing incentive structures and providing effective leadership in linear and matrixed organizational configurations.
- Excel in consensus-building and facilitating efficient communication among teams, leadership, and stakeholders.
- Strategically design engineering staffing plans, manage budgets, conduct rigorous team performance assessments, and deliver impactful compensation strategies.

Domain Expertise

- Specialize in Ads Tech, focusing on Machine Learning Model Evaluation and Observability Infrastructure to improve efficacy of Ads Ranking algorithms.
- Extensive experience FinTech domain, encompassing hedge fund/private equity portfolio valuations, tax accounting, investor allocations, reconciliation, AML compliance, transaction risk calibration and monitoring, order execution/settlement, and sensitive data management (PII and MNPI) within a complex global regulatory landscape.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Meta (f.k.a. Facebook) | New York
Title: Software Engineering Manager

June 2021 - Present | NYC

June 2021 | New York

<u>Role:</u> Senior Engineering Manager, Global Head of Ads Model Evaluation, and Explainable Infrastructure

Org Size: 30+ across multiple locations in North America and Europe (including managers)

Primary Tech Stack: C++, Python, Scribe, Pytorch, Presto, Hive/Spark, My-SQL

Engagements:

- Founded and expanded North America centric engineering org responsible for developing Machine Learning Model Validation, Evaluation and Observability tooling, serving personalized Ads to live production traffic of ~3 billion global users across Meta's Apps
 - Formed strong partnerships and skillfully managed cross-functional relationships, facilitating the rapid growth of the organization from its **inception to comprising over 35 professionals** in two years. Immediate org included engineering managers and senior staff+ level individual contributors. XFNs included TPMs, DS, DE, PE, and business/partner engineering teams.
 - Led the development of organizational culture, vision, strategy, roadmap, goals/OKRs, risk mitigations, development practices, operating rhythms, and production management processes.
 - Conducted regular performance evaluations, provided constructive feedback, oversaw talent management, defined location strategies, and crafted growth plans for both the organization and engineering workforce.



Vaibhav Sabnis

New York | Phone: +1(973) 337 0312 | Email: vaibhav.sabnis@gmail.com | LinkedIn

- Designed observability techniques focused on Machine Learning (ML) performance metrics, significantly enhancing detection and mitigation capabilities within a complex Ads Ranking Stack, reducing Time-to-Detect and Time-to-Mitigate from weeks to minutes.
- Proactively prevented revenue-losses, and successfully met high standards for latency, reliability, power consumption, and scalability resulting in annual savings of over USD 1.4 billion for Meta through the implementation of model validation tools, safeguards, and risk control processes.
- Drive a cross-department initiative aimed at measuring and enhancing engineering operational cost, ultimately driving improvements in developer efficiency, %engineering time spent on operations and improving individual work satisfaction scores.

Goldman Sachs | New York

2020 - 2021 | New York

Title: Technology Vice President

Oct 2020 - June 2021 | New York

Role: Senior Director, NA Head SecDB Core Platform Engineering—Global Markets Division

Org Size: >40+ east coast US (including engineering directors)

Primary Tech: Slang, SecDB, C++, Java, BigQuery, IDE builds (Secview, VSCode extension, IntelliJ), Gitlab, CVS, Kanban

Engagements:

- Led and supported Tech Leads and Managers in driving initiatives for extending adoption of the Slang programming language and enhance overall Sec DB (securities database) runtime ecosystem. This platform served as the foundation for pricing, risk assessment, and analytics for financial instruments.
 - Manage technology guidance, career development, and business stakeholder relationships, while also overseeing technology roadmaps.
 - o Fostered collaborative and open Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC) and successfully established a globally shared, consistent, and highly performant analytics platform.
 - Led modernization of programming language design and implementation, aligning it with contemporary technology trends. This
 included embracing cloud-native principles, fostering cross-technology support, and integrating built-in support for observability
 paradigms.

Morgan Stanley Inc. | New York

2006 - 2020

Title: Executive Director

New York

Role: Senior Director, Global Technology Head for Investor Data – Morgan Stanley Fund Services

Org Size: >100 engineers across multiple global locations (including engineering directors)

<u>Primary Tech:</u> Core Java, Spring boot, REST/SOAP Webservices/APIs, SQL / No-SQL databases, Cloud-Native tooling (Azure), Angular, Websockets, Messaging Queues, open-NLP, OCR & 2D dynamic Barcode Imaging libraries, BOX APIs, GIT and Devops tools

Engagements:

Joined MSFS (a startup group - part of Morgan Stanley), as one of the initial software developers in early 2006. Over the subsequent 15 years, I assumed a pivotal role in orchestrating the remarkable transformation of MSFS into a preeminent global leader in fund serving business. Our distinctiveness stemmed from the deployment of state-of-the-art technology solutions, establishing a prominent presence on Wall Street.

Through a progressive trajectory within the organization, I embarked on a trajectory of continuous advancement within the organization, culminating in my appointment as Senior Director of Technology. In this capacity, I assumed leadership of the Investor Data Tech department, overseeing pivotal initiatives for MSFS.

As a senior leader, I undertook the critical responsibility of developing, designing, and securing alignment with key stakeholders, including C-suite executives, other organizational engineering leaders and client / vendor technology partners. My primary focus was on formulating and executing a comprehensive technology investment, organization growth strategy and roadmaps for an organization of over 100 professionals. This encompassed leading initiatives related to IT transformations, project execution, progress measurement, development environments / tools / operating policies and procedures, and client data management, both in transit and at rest. My achievements



Vaibhay Sabnis

New York | Phone: +1(973) 337 0312 | Email: vaibhav.sabnis@gmail.com | LinkedIn

include the successful implementation of robust risk and control measures to enhance data management, fostering seamless interactions among clients and internal teams.

- [2018-2020] Established a senior engineering team (~10 engineers) focused on AML/KYC & Activity monitoring, directly contributing yearly 7% top-line revenue increase for MSFS. Efforts translated in delivering an industry-first ML model driven point-based ranking tool for analyzing investment and franchise risk.
 - Took charge of driving the technical strategy, roadmap collaborating closely with key stakeholders (AML, company legal, clients and technical vendors/data-providers)
 - Oversaw all aspects of the end-to-end product development & deployment, enabling real-time rule-based screening of suspicious transaction activities and ensuring compliance with stringent US and Cayman AML regulatory standards.
 - o Scaled the functionality to analyze and extract key features multi-millions of documents (emails/pdfs/images) in a batch mode.
- [2017-2020] Conceptualized and led a digital transformation initiative focused on adaptive interview-based web experience for transaction management and investments, aimed to replace physical processing documents, signatures and improving automation/eliminating manual checks.
 - Replaced physical/scan/manual investment process by delivering a configurable web experience for various legal/regulatory templates (contributions, redemptions, transfers, investment/PII attribute changes)
 - Drove technology strategy and implementation projects for integrating electronic signatures using DocuSign.
 - o Rolled-out an inhouse ML based fault-tolerant document data-scraping engine, reducing content extraction time by 75%
 - Scaled backend components to handle ~4 million client tasks per month with an average task execution time of under 1 second, resulting in reduced client interaction time by 40%
- [2014-2020] Managed a globally distributed org of over 40 engineers, overseeing multiple technology projects aimed at modularizing, optimizing, and scaling the FS-Investor Datawarehouse (FSID). Remarkably, reduced back-office staffing needs by 10% YoY, resulting in annual savings of approximately 150 FTEs without compromising client service quality.
 - Drove tech organizational strategy, engineer growth and technology program roadmaps collaborating with senior engineers, stakeholders, and leadership.
 - Successfully met technology compliance goals (SSAE16 certification) for safeguarding client trade-secrets, PII / MNPI data control, effectively preventing misdirected communication.
 - Established a central data warehouse for data management comprising of ~3.5 billion entitlement units, millions of physical documents, thousands of curated attributes.
 - Implemented data de-duplication and centralization strategies while enforcing rigorous standards and APIs, ensuring data integrity.
 - Orchestrated the externalization of data access through APIs, significantly enhancing the usability, scalability, and overall maintenance of client applications and improving API response time by 400% (averaging 200 msec/request)
 - o Focused on implementing single responsibility pattern-based APIs, distributed compute/cache systems, and content validation techniques for serving requests to ~90+ downstream applications (~250K requests/hour).
- [2010-2014] Managed engineering squads (~18 engineers) in the development of Tax and Investor accounting and allocation system, improving sales revenue by 10%, replacing vendor applications by market differentiating in-house builds and meet US/Europe Hedge fund tax/accounting regulatory filing requirements.
 - Drove projects that helped identify wash sales triggering transactions and report on Qualified Dividends.
 - Drove Design, rollout and maintenance of a market-differentiating, efficient and scalable tax investor allocation engine that
 prepared on-demand tax estimates and K-1 filings, by analyzing millions of tax-lots daily against existing client trading activity and
 alert portfolio managers and traders to make tax-efficient trading decision helping generate profits for clients.
 - Co-Managed the rollout of investor economic allocation engines, effectively replacing vendor solutions. This system handled approximately 2 million Account Allocations, fee calculations, and investment Return on Investment (RoR) calculations per period (approximately daily). The development of this system resulted in substantial yearly savings in vendor license costs and provided a competitive advantage for the business.
- [2006-2010] Early senior developer on a growing team (about 3-10 engineers) that build key technology blocks and establish MSFS as a prominent service fund administrator and optimizing business operations.
 - Orove Cash and Payment management allocations that met critical accounting business requirements and facilitated payments in/out of hedge funds. This system efficiently handled all aspects of expense tracking, and generated statement of change reports for hedge fund clients, handling multiple billions of dollar movements across the entire client base.
 - Delivered a MSFS client-billing application, backed by a rate-slabs based billing engine that calculated client bills, generated billing reports, and tracked revenue. This initiative streamlined operations for the MSFS-COO office, eliminating manual tracking processes and improving bill collection rates by 30%



Vaibhav Sabnis

New York | Phone: +1(973) 337 0312 | Email: vaibhav.sabnis@gmail.com | LinkedIn

 Implemented configurable daily reconciliation system that performed position, transaction, and cash-balance reconciliations for all Hedge Fund clients. Developed rule-based 'daily-breaks' auto-commenting module that helped identify trade breaks and reduce break resolution time by 90%

Mastek Ltd. | London - UK, Mumbai - India

Jan 2003 - Jan 2006

Title: Software Programmer

- Developed modules to replace legacy IBM mainframe with distributed design/codebase in healthcare claims processing space.
- Selected to the prestigious Java center of Excellence based on performance amongst 140 new joined graduates within company.
- Contributed to Apache commons open-source ecosystem on-behalf of the company.

EDUCATION/INTERNSHIP

Bachelors in Engineering | Electronics & Telecommunication

June 1998-June 2002

Internship @ Indian Institute of Technology, IIT - Mumbai

First Class with Distinction, Mumbai University, India

June 2001-April 2002

Implemented SIP protocol handshake using VB.Net to make VoIP based phone calls.

INTERESTS:

Travelling, Photography, Capital Markets, Volunteering, Hindustani Music.

